BU Records: Home Economics Department, Inclusive: 1916-1993, undated, Bulk: 1936-77, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Home Economics Department
Inclusive: 1916-1993, undated, Bulk: 1936-77, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/107
Cardwell, Clyde Newton
2 document boxes and 1 oversize box
The Home Economics Department records include correspondence, education materials, literary productions, and photographs relating to Baylor's Home Economics Department.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The history of the Baylor Home Economics Department can be traced back to 1850. Five years after Baylor officially established itself as a university in Independence, Texas, it began teaching home economics classes. In 1933, the Department of Home Economics was established at Baylor in Waco, Texas. At the time, the Department of Home Economics offered three degrees: home economics education, general home economics, and fashion merchandising. The Home Economics Department found its permanent home at the Mary Gibb Jones Home Economics Facility in 1977. In 1994, the department became known as Family and Consumer Sciences.
Scope and Content
The collection begins in 1916 and ends in 1993, with a great deal of the collection being undated. The collection includes personal and departmental correspondence between Mrs. T. C. Cardwell, Home Economics teacher in the 1930s, and others. The Education Materials series includes lesson materials, various governmental forms, and notebooks. The Literary Productions series is the largest group of the collection and includes publications on teaching home economics, various recipes, newspaper and magazine clippings, event marketing ephemera, and other publications related to home-making. Most of the collection was compiled by Clyde Newton Cardwell, first chairman of the Home Economics Department.
Some materials in the collection were compiled by previous Texas Collection staff members over time and kept in subject files. These materials were added to the collection during processing.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection was arranged in no particular order in labeled and unlabeled folders. Currently, the collection is arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Education Materials, III. Literary Productions, and IV: Photographs. Within each series, folders are arranged alphabetically. Within each folder, materials were kept in original order, which is not necessarily chronological order.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/107. Acquired 1978-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
"About Family and Consumer Sciences." Accessed 2017 November 13.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Cardwell, Clyde Newton, -1968 -- Correspondence.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University. Department of Home Economics -- Records and correspondence.
Subjects
Home economics -- Study and teaching -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Articles.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1936-1992, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence produced by the Home Economics Department, including invitations for events. It also contains correspondence of Mrs. T. C. Cardwell during her time as chairman of the Home Economics Department. Some of the correspondence is personal, but most reference the department in some way. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Alumnus Letter, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mrs. T.C. Cardwell, 1936-1940,undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Home Economics Department Event Invitations, 1960-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Education Materials, 1938-1940, undated; 2
  This series contains material related to the education of home economics, including notebooks, lesson materials, and government forms. Most of the material in this series is undated and was collected by Clyde Newton Cardwell. This series is in average condition.
  - Application for Admission: Baylor University Nursery School, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baylor University Infant/Toddler Study Center blank certificate, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Government Forms, Reports, and Vocational Educational, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “Home Management Cottage — Baylor University” Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lesson Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Recipes for Talks and Broadcasts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United States Civil Service Examination for Senior Cook in Prison Service, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Untitled Notebooks (3), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Literary Productions, 1916-1993, undated; 3
  This is the largest series in BU Records: Home Economics Department and contains various publications produced by the Home Economics Department, publications related to home economics and vocational education, recipes published by large companies such as Heinz, and clippings collected by students and Clyde Newton Cardwell. It is in average condition.
  - American Home Economics Association Fact Sheet, c. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Baylor Home Economics Association Directory Booklet, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Baylor Home Economics Newsletters, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baylor’s Philosophy on Home Economics, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Bibliography: Career Opportunities in Home Economics and Dietetics” — Prepared by the Liaison Committee of The American Dietetic Association and The American Home Economics Association, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - A Booklet for the New Nursery School Parent by Baylor University Nursery School, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - “Colleges and Universities Offering Undergraduate Majors in Home Economics”, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “Department of Home Economics: Uniforms and care of Laboratory”, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Elizabeth Barrett Scrapbook — Newspaper & Magazine Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - First Steps in Water Color Painting by Martin F. Gleason, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “A Guide to Evaluation and Improvement — For use in home-management houses, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Harrington Hall Roster, 1945-1956 (Box 3 OVZ)
  - Home Economics Department Event Programs, 1965-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Home Economics Event Flyers and Circulars, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Home Economics Event Guestbook, 1939 (Box 3 OVZ)
  - Home Economics Pamphlets, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Home Economics Week Programs and Schedules, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kappa Omicron Phi: Professional Home Economics, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lena Lawson — Clipping and Articles, 1929-1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. M. M. Allbritton Scrapbook - Clippings and Articles, undated (Box 3 OVZ)
  - National Grocers Bulletin, vol. 24 no. 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “A New Home for Home Economics” by Jane Walker Williamson, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Home-Makers Bulletin, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nutritional Charts for Medical and Other Specialists, 8th edition, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Paper on Home Management House, Annex on Baylor Avenue, and Home Economics Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Preliminary report of Committee on methods: First Training Conference For Distributive Education Called by The United States Office of Education, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Published Recipes, 1916-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - “A Report on the Role of Home Economists in Public Welfare Agencies” by the American Home Economics Association and APWA, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Sunshine Monthly, vol. 20 no. 4, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Texas Public Schools Standards and Activities of the Division of Supervision, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tri-D Newsletter, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vocational Education in Home Economic: Twelve Years of Home Economics Education Under the National Vocational Education Acts, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - WHTATss Annual Meeting: Special Profession Special People program, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1945; 4
  - Pictures of Mrs. Taylor's Clothing Class: Tailoring 272, 1945 April (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)